Inventory of the Iranian Political Opposition Literature collection
Hoover Institution Archives
- Sarbāzān-i Īrān, 1981-1987, undated; 73 (Box 73)
  - Monographs, booklets, and articles (Folder 73)
    - Baqat-i ābād, Ahmad ābād!!, (Toronto: Sarbāzān-i Īrān), booklet, probably 1361 (1982) (Folder 73: 5)
    - Hidīeh-i shāhān, (Toronto: Sarbāzān-i Īrān), monograph, 1360 Mordād (1981 July) (Folder 73: 6)
    - Intizār-i millat, aruzu-yi shāh: hadaf-i shāh, aruzu-yi millat, booklet, (Toronto: Sarbāzān-i Īrān), undated (Folder 73: 7)
    - Millī va ārtish-i shāhinshāhī, (Toronto: Sarbāzān-i Īrān), monograph, 1360 (1981) (Folder 73: 8)
    - The Moderate Mullahs, (Toronto: Soldiers of Iran), articles translated into English by M.A.I., probably 1985 (Folder 73: 9)
    - Ou chinīn bud?, (Toronto: Sarbāzān-i Īrān), monograph, 1361 Mordād (1982 July) (Folder 73: 10)
    - Pāsukhnāmeh, (Toronto: Sarbāzān-i Īrān), booklet, 1360 Ordibihisht (1981 April) (Folder 73: 11)
    - Payām-i 'alīhazrat-i Rizā Pahlavī pādshāh-i īrān bimināsbat-i sālruz-i inqilāb mashrutiat-i īrān, (Toronto: Sarbāzān-i Irān), booklet, 1360 Mordād (1981 July) (Folder 73: 12)
    - Sag'hā-yi hār, (Toronto: Sarbāzān-i Īrān), booklet, 1363 Bahman (1984 January) (Folder 73: 13)
      Includes pictures of 24 mullahs, with satirical captions
    - Sāltānāt va massulīat, (Toronto: Sarbāzān-i Īrān), monograph, 1361 Esfand (1982 February) (Folder 73: 14)
    - Sukhānī bā ham-i mīhananam, Reza Pahlavi, 1362 Farvardīn (1983 April) (Folder 73: 15)
      Includes English translation
- Other Iranian Political Opposition Groups, 1961-2003, undated; 74-79, 84 (Box 74-79, 84)
  Arranged in alphabetical order by name of organization
  - Anjumān-i āzādī, newspapers, 1362 (1983) (Folder 74: 1)
  - Ārtash-i rahā'i baksh-i īrān, newspapers, 1359 (1980-1981) (Folder 84: 5)
  - Boniad-i Mosaddeq (Mossadeq Foundation), Paris, serial monograph, 1363 (1984) (Folder 74: 2)
  - Constitutional Councils, Washington D.C., press releases and statements, 1985 May-July (Folder 74: 3)
  - Federāsīyun-i Āllemān, booklet, 1356 (1977) (Folder 74: 4)
  - Guruh-i āzādi khvahān pīshru, booklets, 1361 (1982) (Folder 74: 5)
  - Guruh-i bi-su-yi ittihād, newsletter, 1372-1373 (1993-1994) (Folder 74: 6)
  - Guruh-i ittihād-i kumunīst, monographs and booklets, 1356 (1977) (Folder 74: 7-9)
  - Guruh-i pasdarān-i qānun-i isāsī, newspapers, 1365-1366 (1986-1987) (Folder 74: 10)
  - Guruh-i pīshru, booklet, undated (Folder 74: 11)
  - Hayat-i muāsīs-i federāsīyun-i shurāhāi-i pananhandīgān-i īrānī (Constituent Committee of the Federation of Iranian Refugees Councils), newsletter, 1990 January (Folder 74: 12)
  - Hizb-i dimukrātik-i mardum-ī irān, monograph, 1369 Mordād (1980 July) (Folder 74: 13)
  - Hizb-i Īrān, newspaper, 1357 Day (1978 December) (Folder 84: 5)
  - Hizb-i nāsīyunālīst kārgarān-i īrān, newsletters, 1361 Mordād-1362 Farvardīn (1982 August-1983 March) (Folder 74: 14-15)
  - Hizb-i Panīrānīst, 1340-1362 (1961-1983) (Folder 74)
    - Booklets and monographs, 1340-1362 (1961-1983) (Folder 74: 16-17)
    - Newspapers and newsletters, 1359-1360 (1980-1981) (Folder 74: 18-19)
      Includes issue nos. 14-20 of Millat and nos. 2-6 of Pandar
  - Hizb-i ranjbarān, newsletters, magazines, and booklets, 1358-1362 (1979-1983) (Folder 75: 1-3)
  - Hizb-i ranjbarān (contd.), newspapers, 1359 (1980) (Folder 84: 6)
    Includes 14 issues of Ranjbarān
  - Hizb-i rastakhīz-i īrān, newspapers, probably late 1970s (Folder 84: 7)
    Includes issues 8-13, 17-22, 24, 26-27, and 33 of Shāhfarāz Āriān (published in West Germany)
  - Ittihād barāh-yi āzādī-i kār, booklet, 1361 (1982) (Folder 75: 4)
    Includes Andīsheh-yi Inqilāb, shumārah-i 10
  - Ittihād-i dimukrātīk mardum-i īrān, newsletter, 1358 (1979) (Folder 75: 5)
  - Ittihād-i mubārāzāh dar rāh-i ijād-i hizb-i tabaqah-i kārgar, booklets, 1358-1359 (1979-1980) (Folder 75: 6)
  - Jabhah-i āhiāi-i mashrutīat-i irān, serial monograph, 1361 (1982) (Folder 75: 7)
  - Jabhah-i āzādībaksh-i millī-i īrān, booklet, 1351 (1972) (Folder 75: 8)
  - Jabhah-i dimukrātīk-i inqilābi zahmatkishān-i īrān, booklet, 1363 (1984) (Folder 75: 9)
  - Jabhah-i dimukrātīk-i millī-i īrān, newspapers, 1358 (1979) (Folder 75: 10)
  - Jabhah-i Mosāddeqī'hā-yi īrān, booklets and journals, 1359-1361 (1980-1982) (Folder 75: 11)
  - Jam'āh-i dafā' az hiquq bashir dar īrān (Leagues for the Defense of Human Rights in Iran), bulletins, newsletters, and journals, 1362-1363 (1983-1984) (Folder 75: 12-13)
  - Jam'āh-i dafā' az hiquq bashir dar īrān (Leagues for the Defense of Human Rights in Iran), bulletins, newsletters, and journals, 1364-1382 (1985-2003) (Folder 76: 1-5)
  - Jam'āh-i farāq iltihasilān-i āzādīkhavahān-i irān muqīm āllemān federāl va berlin qarbī, booklet, circa 1970s (Folder 76: 6)
  - Jam'īat-i āzādī, booklets, undated (Folder 76: 7)
  - Jam'īat-i āzādī, newspapers, 1358-1359 (1979-1980) (Folder 84: 8)
    Includes two issues of Nafarman
  - Jam'īat-i āzādīkhāhān-i īrān, newsletters, 1357-1364 (1978-1985) (Folder 76: 8)
    Includes nos. 7-10 of Āzādī-i Īrān
  - Jam'īat-i dafā' az dimukrāsī va istiqāl-i īrān, serial monographs, 1364-1367 (1985-1988) (Folder 76: 9-10)
    Includes 6 issues of the serial Rāh-i Āzādī
  - Jaryān-i inqilābī-i susiālīstī, booklets, 1364 (1985), undated (Folder 76: 11)
  - Jumhurī'khvahān-i millat-i īrān, journals and declarations, 1363-1364 (1984-1985) (Folder 76: 12-13)
  - Jumhurī'khvahān-i millat-i īrān (contd.), newspapers, 1366-1367 (1987-1988) (Folder 77: 1-4)
  - Jumhurī'khvahān-i millat-i īrān, newspapers, 1368-1369 (1989-1990) (Folder 84: 8)
    Includes issues 17-23 and 30 of the monthly newspaper of the National Republicans of Iran
  - Junbish-i dimukrātīk inqilāb-i zahmatkishān-i īrān, monograph, 1364 (1985) (Folder 77: 5)
  - Junbish-i kumunīst-i īrān, booklets, 1357-1361 (1978-1982) (Folder 77: 6)
  - Junbish-i musalmān-i mubārāz, booklets, 1356-1358 (1977-1979) (Folder 77: 7)
  - Junbish-i tanbāku, monograph, undated (Folder 77: 8)
  - Kārgarān-i san'at-i naft, journal, probably 1980s (Folder 77: 9)
  - Kārgarān va zahamatkishān pīshru-i junub garb-i Tihrān, newsletter, 1359 (1980) (Folder 77: 10)
  - Kumiteh barāh-yi dafā' az hiquq bashir va pīshbarādān dar īrān, journal photocopy, 1356-1357 (1977-1978) (Folder 77: 11-14)
    Includes issues 0-15
  - Kumiteh barāh-yi dafā' az hiquq bashir va pīshbarādān dar īrān (contd.), constitution, 1357 Farvardīn (1978 March) (Folder 78: 1)
  - Mudaf'īan susīālīsm-i 'almī, newspapers, 1377 (1998) (Folder 78: 2)
  - Nahzat-i mashrutīyat-i īrān (The Constitutional Movement of Iran), magazines, 1983 (Folder 78: 3)
    Includes issues 1-2
  - Nāsīyunālīst'hā-yi mutihād-i īrān, newspapers, 1365 (1986) (Folder 78: 4)
  - Organization of Active Constitutionalist Iranians (O.A.I.C.), booklet, undated (Folder 78: 5)
  - Pilātfurm-i chap, Chicago, booklets, 1982-1983 (Folder 78: 6)
  - Razmandigān-i āzādi tabaqeh-yi kārgar dar sharāyat-i kānunī, booklet, 1358 (1979) (Folder 78: 7)
  - Sāzmān-i dānishjuyān-i īrāni dar Holānd, bulletin, 1366 (1988) (Folder 78: 8)
  - Sāzmān-i dānishjuyān-i īrānī pilātfurm-i chap, Houston, booklets, 1359-1363 (1980-1984) (Folder 78: 9)
  - Sāzmān-i inqilābī, monographs, 1357-1358 (1978-1979) (Folder 78: 10)
  - Sāzmān-i inqilābīyun-i kumunīst (Mārksīst-Linīnīst), booklets, 1351-1354 (1972-1975), undated (Folder 78: 11-13)
  - Sāzmān-i ittihād-i chap, newspapers, 1358-1359 (1979-1980) (Folder 78: 14)
  - Sāzmān-i kārgarān-i inqilābī-ī irān, booklet, 1364 (1985) (Folder 78: 15)
  - Sāzmān-i Mārksist-Linīnīst Tufān, booklets and journals, 1347-1356 (1968-1977), undated (Folder 79: 1-3)
  - Sāzmān-i niqāb, newspapers, 1361-1363 (1982-1984) (Folder 79: 4-5)
  - Sāzmān-i susīālīst'hā-yi īran, journals, 1363-1364 (1984-1985) (Folder 79: 6)
    Includes 5 issues of Junbish-i Susialīstī
  - Shurā-yi muttāhid-i chap barā-yi dimukrāsī va istiqāl, booklets and newspapers, 1360-1364 (1981-1985) (Folder 79: 7-8)
    Includes issue nos. 18-19, 21-22, and 26-29 of Payām Āzādi
  - Unidentified, assorted booklets and newsletters, 1357-1363 (1978-1984) (Folder 79: 9)
- Other Printed Matter, 1969-1993; 80-83 (Box 80-83: 2)
  Includes printed matter that is not affiliated with a particular political organization. Many of the works reflect on the theory and rhetoric of the political opposition and Iranian revolution in general
  Arranged in three groups: Serials, Monographs and booklets, and Translated works. Translated works are arranged in alphabetical order by author.
  - Serials (Folder 80-82)
    - Āghāzī-i naw, shumarah-i 1, (Berkeley, Calif.: Intishārat-i Aghāzī-i Naw), journal and pamphlet, 1364 va 1367 (1985 and 1988) (Folder 80: 1)
      Includes a publication of the journal
    - Akhtar, daftar-i 6-7, (Saarbruken, Sweden: Intishārat-i Bāztāb), journals, 1367-1368 (1988-1989) (Folder 80: 2)
    - 'Alim va Jam'āh, sāl-i 7, shumārah-i 41, (Alexandria, Va.: s.n.), journal, 1364 Ābān (1985 October) (Folder 80: 3)
    - Āzaraksh, sāl-i 3, shumārah-i 12, newspaper, 1357 Day (1978 December) (Folder 80: 4)
    - Dulat va inqilāb, shumārah-i 1, (London: s.n.), journal, 1361 (1982) (Folder 80: 5)
    - Gāhnāmeh-yi jomhourī, (Occasional Republican Papers), shumārah-i 6, journal, 1363 Āzar (1984 November) (Folder 80: 6)
      Issue includes articles by M. Shu'ā'īyān and Cosroe Chaqueri
    - Inqilāb va susīālism, (Paris: Olivier le Cour), shumārah-i 1-4, journals and magazines, 1361 Ābān-1362 Shahrivar (1982 October-1983 August) (Folder 80: 7)
    - Īrān emrooz, shumārah-i 28, newspaper, 1360 Ābān (1981 October) (Folder 80: 8)
    - Īrānshahr, newspapers, 1360-1362; 1371 (1981-1984; 1993) (Folder 80-81)
      - Dawreh-yi 3, shumārah-i 20, 1360 Mordād 16 (1981 August 7) (Folder 80: 9)
      - Dawreh-yi 6, shumārah-i 26-27, 36, 41, 44-47, 49-50, 1361 Shahrivar 26-Esfand 20 (1982 September 17-1983 March 11) (Folder 80: 10-11)
      - Dawreh-yi 7, shumārah-i 1-8, 1362 Farvardīn 1-Ordibihisht 16 (1983 March 21-May 6) (Folder 80: 12-13)
      - Dawreh-yi 7 (contd.), shumārah-i 9-38, 40-42, 1362 Ordibihisht 23-Day 16 (1983 May 13-1984 January 6) (Folder 81: 1-8)
      - Dawreh-yi 8, shumārah-i 1, 1362 Esfand 26 (1984 March 16) (Folder 81: 9)
      - Dawreh-yi ?, shumārah-i 2, (Paris: s.n.), 1371 Esfand (1993 February) (Folder 81: 10)
    - Kan va kāv, shumārah-i 4 va shumārah-i vīzheh, (London: Kanokav), magazine and journal, 1976 November and 1978 (Folder 81: 11)
    - Masā'il-i inqilāb va susiālīsm, shumārah-i 1-6, serial monographs, 1353-1355 (1974-1976) (Folder 82: 1-2)
    - Millat-i bīdār, dawreh-i 2, shumārah-i 8, (Beverly Hills, Calif.: Melli Publishing House, Inc.), magazine, 1362 Bahman (1984 January) (Folder 82: 3)
    - Nazm-i novīn, daftar-i 2-6, (Tehran: Intishārat-i Nazm), 1358-1363 (1979-1984) (Folder 82: 4-6)
      Theoretical journal reflecting on the Islamic regime at the time of its inception
    - Qalām, sāl-i 2, shumārah-i 6, (Berlin: s.n.), booklet, 1356 (1977) (Folder 82: 7)
    - Zamān-i naw, shumārah-i 10-12, serial monographs, 1364 Ābān va 1365 Shahrivar (1985 November and 1986 August) (Folder 82: 8)
  - Monographs and booklets (Folder 82-83)
    - Bar mā cheh guzasht?, monograph, undated (Folder 82: 9)
      Essays and reflections on Iran and nationalism
    - Barā-yi najat az siqut-i siyāsi va ijtimā'i-i mubārāzāh kunim, Hassan Massali, undated (Folder 82: 10)
    - Bāzi bā ātash: tahlīlī az inqilāb...? īrān, Muhassan Said, booklet, 1357 (1978) (Folder 82: 11)
    - Contemporary Iranian Exile Press Handbook to the Dissident Press of Revolutionary Iran, Wolfgang Behn and Willi Hofig (Berlin: s.n.), booklet, 1983 (Folder 83: 1)
    - Dar bāreh-yi bīmazī az masā'il-i Hizb-i Tudah-'i Īrān, (Paris: s.n.), monograph, 1348 Farvardīn (1969 March) (Folder 83: 2)
    - Īrān kojā mīravad?, K. Pasadas, booklet, 1358 (1979) (Folder 83: 3)
    - Istrātizhī va tāktīkī-i hizb-i bolshevīk va mubārāzāh barāh-yi dīktāturī-i prulitarīā (1903-1917), booklet, undated (Folder 83: 4)
    - Mazduran karmalin, Mahmoud Piraih (S.l.: Nashr-i Mehr), booklet, circa 1970s (Folder 83: 5)
    - Oktopus-i sad pā!, booklet, 1357 (1979) (Folder 83: 6)
    - Oligārshī yā khadanhā-i hakumatigar-i īrān, Abulfazal Qassemi, monograph, 1357 Āzar (1978 October) (Folder 83: 7)
    - Pīshnihād va tarh-i t'āsis-i "jabhah-i hakumīat-i millī-i īrān", Hassan Nazih, monograph, 1362 (1983) (Folder 83: 8)
    - Qarbāniyān ist'amar dar īrān, Abul Fazal Qassemi, (Tehran: Raz), 1354 (1975) (Folder 83: 9)
    - Rāh-i mā, report, circa 1981 (Folder 83: 10)
    - Tufān-i araz, (Copenhagen: s.n.), 1372 (1993) (Folder 83: 11)
      Includes two publications focusing on north and south Azerbaijan
    - Miscellaneous booklets, monographs, and pamphlets, 1357-1366 (1978-1987) (Folder 83: 12-14)
      Includes works by Dr. Yunis Pasabinab and Dr. Cosroe Chaqueri. Also includes one pamphlet in Arabic
  - Translated works (Folder 83)
    Dates given are those of the translation and not of the original work
    - V.I. Lenin (Folder 83)
      - Abtikār-i 'azīm, (People's Republic of China: Idāra-yi nasriyat-i zabānah-i khāriji), monograph, 1355 (1976) (Folder 83: 15)
      - Daw tāktīk-i susīāl dimukrāsī dar inqilāb-i dimukrātīkī (Two Tactics of Social-Democracy in the Democratic Revolution), (S.l.: Intishārat-i Paygāh), monograph, 1357 (1978) (Folder 83: 15)
      - Impirīālīsm bihmasābeh-yi bālātarīn marhālih sarmāyih darī (Imperialism, the Highest Stage of Capitalism), (People's Republic of China: s.n.), monograph, 1354 (1975) (Folder 83: 15)
    - Karl Marx and Friedrich Engels. Mānīfest-i Hizb-i Kumunīst (The Communist Manifesto), chāp-i 3, monograph, 1978 (Folder 83: 16-17)
      Includes a compilation of writings by Marx, Engels, and Lenin titled "Zanān va junbish'hā-yi āzādībaksh" (Women and the National Liberation Movement), 1355 (1976)
    - Joseph Stalin. Rajh beh usul-i Linīnīsm (The Principles of Leninism), (People's Republic of China: Idārā-yi nasriyat-i zabānāh-i khāriji), monograph, 1976 (Folder 83: 18)
- Incremental Materials (Box 84-87)
  This addition to the collection has not yet been described.